Guide to the Thomas M. Williams Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Thomas M. Williams papers
1895-1948
SC0191
Williams, Thomas M., 1871-1947
0.75 Linear feet
Correspondence, notes, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia pertaining to Williams' affiliation with Stanford University and Palo Alto Hospital, including syllabi and notes from classes, 1895-96; his World War I service in Scotland; and his family. Also includes guest book from the family cabin, 1937-47, which includes notes and signatures of Herbert Hoover, Lou Henry Hoover, and their children
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Rhona Williams, 1987-88, Ethel McGiness, 1988, and Fred Glover, 1988.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Stanford Class of 1897. Williams earned his MD at Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1901. He was one of Palo Alto's first physicians, establishing his practice there in 1904; he continued a close affiliation with Stanford, serving on its Board of Athletic Control from 1916 to 1928.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, notes, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia pertaining to Williams' affiliation with Stanford University and Palo Alto Hospital, including syllabi and notes from classes, 1895-96; his World War I service in Scotland; and his family. Also includes guest book from the family cabin, 1937-47, which includes notes and signatures of Herbert Hoover, Lou Henry Hoover, and their children
Access Terms
Allabach, Lucy.; Glover, Frederic O.; Heath, Harold, 1868-1951.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.; Palo Alto Hospital (Palo Alto, Calif.).; Stanford University. Department of Athletics.; Williams, Dora Moody.; Williams, Thomas M., 1871-1947; Photoprints.; Williams family.; World War, 1914-1918.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Obituaries and other articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes re: Stanford Stadium controversy; press release about Stadium construction, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Mrs. Dora Moody Williams, 7 Nov. 1928, tl. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Pearce Mitchell luncheon, June 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Stanford - Palo Alto Hospital, March 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wooley Camp Association (list of families camping) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1938-48: letters from Harold and Elsie Heath; Lucy (Allabach) Lichty with photographs of student picnics 1893; Ray Lyman Wilbur; and Arthur and Grace Clark with illustrated map of San Juan Hill neighborhood on Stanford's campus (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Christmas cards from Louise Culver, 1943-45 and undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Christmas cards from Alice Windsor Kimball, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Williams and the Stanford "Indian": typescript excerpt (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Emma Rendtorff, "Magic Waters": typescript of play dedicated to Dr. Williams and program, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Russian money, c. 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Evolution lecture outlines with class notes by Williams, ca. 1895 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Syllabus for History 5a with notes by Williams on reverse, ca. 1895 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Syllabus for European Civilization (with bibliographies, excerpts, study questions), 1895/96 year (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Mrs. Dora Moody Williams to Auntie Kate (Mrs. William L. Smith), 3 Nov. 1930 (photocopy, the White House letterhead) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs (15): Thomas Williams, family and friends (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1. Thomas W. Williams with Norman Scofield
    2. Portrait of Williams 1900 or 1901
    3. Dr. Williams at desk
    4. Family portrait, from left: Rhona, Dr. Willliams, Mrs. Williams, Elizabeth
    5. Snapshot of Rhona and Betty with father
    6. Williams in his Autocar
    7. Williams' office building, downtown Palo Alto
    8. Williams with Sam McDonald and unidentified man
    9. Williams in field, ca. 1901
    10. Williams in kilt, Strattnpeffer, Scotland, 1918
    11. Williams in military uniform with Mrs. Williams (?)
    12. Portrait of Williams in dress military uniform, 1917
    13. Williams in front of trees - "Dad at cabin"
    14. Dora Estey Moody Williams in her wedding dress, 1901
    15. Williams at a football game
  - Strattnpeffer Naval Hospital, Scotland: includes photographs, souvenir photo album, postcards and a reminiscence by Edith May Lyon - a nurse who served with Dr. Williams at Strattnpeffer during World War I (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Guest book from family cabin, 1937-47 (Box 2)